<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-23T17:09:56+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Biodiversity database of West Africa</title><link href="/biodiversity-database-west-africa/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biodiversity database of West Africa" /><published>2023-09-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-09-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/biodiversity-database-west-africa/"><![CDATA[<p>The biodiversity database of West Africa is a service provided to Project Marafrica with the main aim of developing a stable, straightforward and flexible framework for sharing biodiversity data, making publicly available all the biodiversity records of the Banc D’Arguin National Park and the Bijagós archipelago to inform managers, scientists and the general public.</p>

<div style="padding: 20px" class="border-radius-05 bg-gray font-family-secondary font-small text-dark">
Explore the webpage at <a target="_black" href="https://www.marafrica.net">https://www.marafrica.net</a>.
</div>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/project-9-3.png" alt="Graphical interface" style="max-height: 525px;" /></p>

<p>Project Marafrica is a network for monitoring, integrating and assessing marine biodiversity data along the west africa to understand, predict and mitigate climatic / oceanographic changes. It is funded by the Aga-Khan Foundation and FCT-Portugal and Project STM - Survi des Tortues Marines.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A database structured under Darwin Core standards, offering a stable, straightforward and flexible framework for sharing biodiversity data to managers, scientists and the general public.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Heatwaves are more intense and persist longer in deeper waters</title><link href="/marine-heatwaves-more-intense-persist-longer-deeper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heatwaves are more intense and persist longer in deeper waters" /><published>2023-09-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-09-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-heatwaves-more-intense-persist-longer-deeper/"><![CDATA[<p>The world’s oceans have reached their highest recorded temperatures in 2023, and it is forecasted that the intensity, duration, and frequency of marine heatwaves - defined as periods of elevated sea temperatures lasting at least five days - will continue to increase throughout the century. Until now, the impacts and projections of these events have focused on the sea surface, however, localized observations suggest that marine heatwaves can occur below the surface and persist for years. The rising of ocean temperatures has profound consequences for the planet’s geochemical and biological systems, directly affecting marine flora and fauna, and therefore the resources humans depend on.</p>

<p>Using global-level sea temperature observations and reanalysis data, our reseearch group estimated the duration and intensity of marine heatwaves from 1993 to 2019 at depths down to 2,000 meters. The research published in the journal Nature Climate Change, shows that the highest intensity of marine heatwaves is not at the surface but in the subsurface, specifically between 50 and 250 meters deep. “Against our initial expectations, we found that marine heat waves are more intense below the surface, and their duration can last up to double, when compared to the surface,” notes Eliza Fragkopoulou, the leading author of the study.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/figure2-b.webp" alt="Heatwaves are intense and persist in deeper waters" style="max-height: 625px;" /></p>

<p>We combined these findings with data on marine species ranges, and predicted that subsurface biodiversity could be at risk due to higher cumulative intensity (an indicator of thermal stress) in the first 250 meters. Jorge Assis, who led the research explains: “Across the globe, we identified regions of higher risk for marine biodiversity, including significant portions of the Indian and North Atlantic Oceans, where high cumulative heatwave intensity coincides with areas of predicted high species sensitivity to thermal stress. What we’ve discovered is that beyond readily detectable surface effects, such as losses of ecosystem structuring species of mangrove and kelp forests and coral reefs, marine heatwaves can have profound effects on deeper biodiversity, down to 250 meters.”</p>

<p>A noteworthy aspect of this study is the extension of temperature changes from the surface to greatest depths. However, temperature data from deep areas should be taken with caution, especially data prior to 2004, when a more reliable measurement system was implemented. In addition to temperature increases, other changes in ocean conditions need consideration. Temperature extremes are expected to redistribute marine species from the surface to the deep ocean, however, additional constrains, such as low oxygen regions, may hinder such redistribution, with unpredictable consequences. In this context, additional monitoring of marine biodiversity under ongoing extreme climate conditions is needed to better understand and predict their effects.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Global analysis shows deep marine biodiversity facing higher risk of exposure to the cumulative effect of intense and prolonged heatwave events.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Oceanographic connectivity explains the intra-specific diversity of mangrove forests</title><link href="/oceanographic-connectivity-explains-diversity-mangrove-forests/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Oceanographic connectivity explains the intra-specific diversity of mangrove forests" /><published>2023-08-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/oceanographic-connectivity-explains-diversity-mangrove-forests/"><![CDATA[<p>Our research group has recently conducted a groundbreaking study that sheds light on the critical role of ocean currents in shaping the genetic diversity of mangroves. Mangrove ecosystems are renowned for their ecological importance, providing valuable services like carbon sequestration, coastal protection, and habitats for various species.</p>

<p>Traditionally, scientists attributed regional differences in mangrove populations and species to historical climate changes, ongoing climate shifts, and human disturbances. However, this study reveals that ocean currents are equally pivotal factors shaping the dynamics of mangrove biodiversity and conservation.</p>

<p>Using state-of-the-art biophysical modeling techniques, we assessed the extent to which mangrove populations are interconnected via ocean currents. These estimates were then validated using genetic data from diverse mangrove species across the globe. The study challenges conventional approaches that rely solely on geographic distances, instead underscoring the critical role that ocean currents play in connecting mangrove populations over vast distances, sometimes spanning thousands of kilometers.</p>

<p>Our lead authors, Lidiane Gouvêa and Jorge Assis, emphasize the far-reaching implications of these findings. They point out that future alterations in ocean current patterns could lead to the isolation and divergence of mangrove populations. Over time, this could result in reduced biodiversity, increased risks of regional extinctions, and direct consequences for the native communities in tropical countries that rely on the species within mangrove forests.</p>

<p>In summary, our research group’s study highlights how ocean currents significantly influence the genetic diversity of mangroves. It underscores the urgent need for the preservation of these vital ecosystems and the species dependent on them.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The crucial role of ocean currents in shaping mangrove genetic diversity, challenging previous assumptions and emphasizing the importance of preserving these ecosystems.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Biophysical modelling and graph theory identify key connectivity hubs in the Mediterranean marine reserve network.</title><link href="/biophysical-modelling-identify-hubs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biophysical modelling and graph theory identify key connectivity hubs in the Mediterranean marine reserve network." /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/biophysical-modelling-identify-hubs/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Diverse approaches to understanding aquaculture in a changing climate</title><link href="/approaches-understanding-aquaculture-climate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diverse approaches to understanding aquaculture in a changing climate" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/approaches-understanding-aquaculture-climate/"><![CDATA[<p>This project aims to bring together various disciplines to investigate the impact of climate change on aquaculture. We will employ climate and species distribution models, as well as genome sequencing and SNP profiling, to advance our understanding of aquaculture suitability and population dynamics in the face of changing environmental conditions.</p>

<p>Our first objective involves the development of climate analog models based on relevant abiotic parameters in aquaculture. These models will allow us to predict changes in aquaculture suitability on an EEZ (Exclusive Economic Zone) scale.</p>

<p>Subsequently, we will leverage our expertise in genetics to delve into the genetic population structure of Saccharina latissima, a seaweed of increasing interest in European aquaculture. This study will span climate gradients and will compare farmed and wild populations of this seaweed species.</p>

<p>Furthermore, we aim to explore strategies for integrating information from various sources, including modeling and genetics, to promote sustainable aquaculture development. This effort is critical for addressing the challenges posed by climate change in the aquaculture industry.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A project to enhance aquaculture sustainability and suitability while fostering interdisciplinary collaboration.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">High-performance computing projects climate change impacts on biodiversity</title><link href="/high-performance-computing-projects-climate-change-biodiversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="High-performance computing projects climate change impacts on biodiversity" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/high-performance-computing-projects-climate-change-biodiversity/"><![CDATA[<p>The project embarks on a mission to understand the profound impact of climate change on marine biodiversity at a global scale. Empirical evidence has shown significant shifts in the distribution and behavior of marine life due to climate change, with species moving poleward, equatorward, and changing depths. As greenhouse gas emissions continue to rise, the vulnerability of biodiversity escalates, potentially leading to substantial losses, from individual genes to entire ecosystems. However, traditional assessments of these impacts often fall short, relying on climate velocity indicators that consider temperature alone, neglecting other critical factors like oxygen levels, pH, and primary productivity. Additionally, they overlook the role of oceanographic connectivity, which can restrict species’ ability to adapt to shifting environmental conditions, particularly for species with limited dispersal capabilities.</p>

<p>Our research team is poised to address these challenges comprehensively. We will employ high-performance computing and advanced algorithms to develop an innovative approach that combines climate change exposure assessments with oceanographic connectivity estimates. This approach will help us identify regions where marine biodiversity faces potential extinction, regions of persistence, and ocean-accessible climatic corridors.</p>

<p>Experiments will span from the year 2020 to 2100, examining various scenarios of global change. We will consider multiple environmental predictors, including sea surface temperature, oxygen levels, productivity, and pH, while factoring in the direction and intensity of ocean currents. By identifying analogs in climate conditions through time, we aim to pinpoint sites where conditions will resemble those of current habitats. Oceanographic connectivity will be incorporated into our analysis, allowing us to account for the dispersal limitations of marine species. We will use advanced mathematical techniques, including sigma dissimilarity and anisotropic resistance surfaces, parameterized with ocean current data.</p>

<p>In summary, our project aims to provide valuable insights into the future of marine biodiversity under the influence of climate change. Our findings will contribute to informed conservation and management policies, aligning with the Sustainable Development Goals 9, 13, and 14 of the 2030 Agenda and aiding the IPCC’s impact assessments.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Experiments will identify regions of extinction, persistence and ocean-accessible, climatic corridors for biodiversity.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Marine Protected Areas Europe</title><link href="/marine-protected-areas-europe-horizon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marine Protected Areas Europe" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-protected-areas-europe-horizon/"><![CDATA[<p>MPA Europe uses a holistic range of measures that include the range of biodiversity from species to ecosystems, including habitats, areas will be prioritised using systematic conservation planning software. This enables alternative weighting of variables and multiple scenarios and thus support wider marine spatial planning.</p>

<p>The project adopts an interdisciplinary approach, employing comprehensive measures of biodiversity that encompass variation both within and between species and ecosystems. It also considers various environmental variables, carbon cycle dynamics, and climate change scenarios. Our team consists of experts in marine biology, taxonomy, ecology, oceanography, biogeochemistry, biogeography, MPA network design, benthic habitat mapping, carbon dynamics, as well as species distribution and climate modeling.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/MPAinfographic-1500x844.png" alt="Graphical interface" style="max-height: 925px;" /></p>

<p>The project is ambitious in committing to achieve several firsts in terms of products based on new data and analyses: (1) Maps of an optimal MPA network in European seas prioritised for biodiversity protection and blue carbon benefits; (2) Maps of species richness in European seas based on multiple indicators, including actual observed data, statistical estimators, and modelled geographic range maps; (3) Potential geographic distributions of important biogenic habitats in European seas.</p>

<div style="padding: 20px" class="border-radius-05 bg-gray font-family-secondary font-small text-dark">
Explore the webpage of the project at <a target="_black" href="https://mpa-europe.eu/">www.mpa-europe.eu</a>.
</div>

<p><br />
MPA Europe project has been approved under HORIZON-CL6-2021-BIODIV-01-12 — Improved science based maritime spatial planning and identification of marine protected areas.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[MPA Europe will map the optimal locations for marine protected areas in European seas.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Modeling Aquaculture Suitability in a Climate Change Future</title><link href="/aquaculture-suitability-climate-change/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modeling Aquaculture Suitability in a Climate Change Future" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/aquaculture-suitability-climate-change/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">A dataset of cold-water coral distribution records</title><link href="/dataset-cold-water-coral-distribution-records/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A dataset of cold-water coral distribution records" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dataset-cold-water-coral-distribution-records/"><![CDATA[<p>Understanding and monitoring biodiversity patterns, both present and future, is paramount for effective conservation and management strategies. However, the quality of species distribution data often leaves much to be desired, plagued by spatial and taxonomic errors. Additionally, the lack of standardized formats for sharing these datasets hinders seamless integration and interoperability.</p>

<p>In response to these challenges, we present a meticulously curated and quality-controlled dataset encompassing the diversity and distribution of cold-water corals. These remarkable organisms play a vital role in providing ecosystem services and are vulnerable to the impacts of human activities and climate change.</p>

<p>Our dataset employs the term “cold-water corals” to encompass species from various orders, including Alcyonacea, Antipatharia, Pennatulacea, Scleractinia, Zoantharia of the subphylum Anthozoa, and order Anthoathecata of the class Hydrozoa. To compile this valuable resource, distribution records were meticulously collated from multiple sources, standardized following the Darwin Core Standard, and subjected to rigorous quality control measures. Taxonomic errors were corrected, and potential vertical and geographic distribution errors were meticulously flagged, all based on peer-reviewed published literature and expert consultation.</p>

<p>The result is a comprehensive dataset comprising 817,559 high-quality records encompassing 1,170 accepted species of cold-water corals. These records are made openly available under the FAIR principle, ensuring Findability, Accessibility, Interoperability, and Reusability of the data. This dataset stands as the most up-to-date reference for global cold-water coral diversity. It holds immense potential for the scientific community, offering insights into biodiversity patterns and their underlying drivers. Researchers can leverage this resource to identify regions of high biodiversity and endemicity, as well as to project potential redistribution of cold-water corals under future climate change scenarios.</p>

<p>Furthermore, this dataset is a valuable tool for managers and stakeholders engaged in biodiversity conservation. It can guide prioritization actions aimed at mitigating biodiversity loss, ensuring the continued health and resilience of cold-water coral ecosystems. By sharing this wealth of information, we hope to contribute to a deeper understanding of these vital marine organisms and promote their protection in an ever-changing world.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data" /><category term="Biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding and monitoring biodiversity patterns, both present and future, is paramount for effective conservation and management strategies. However, the quality of species distribution data often leaves much to be desired, plagued by spatial and taxonomic errors. Additionally, the lack of standardized formats for sharing these datasets hinders seamless integration and interoperability.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Carbon density in boreal forests responds non-linearly to temperature: An example from the Greater Khingan Mountains</title><link href="/carbon-density-responds-non-linearly-temperature/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carbon density in boreal forests responds non-linearly to temperature: An example from the Greater Khingan Mountains" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/carbon-density-responds-non-linearly-temperature/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>