<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-07T15:45:14+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The key role of seaweed forests in global carbon sequestration</title><link href="/past-future-climate-effects-surfgrasses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The key role of seaweed forests in global carbon sequestration" /><published>2024-06-01T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-01T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/past-future-climate-effects-surfgrasses/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The key role of seaweed forests in global carbon sequestration</title><link href="/seaweed-forests-global-carbon-sequestration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The key role of seaweed forests in global carbon sequestration" /><published>2024-05-20T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-20T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/seaweed-forests-global-carbon-sequestration/"><![CDATA[<p>The coastal ocean plays a crucial role as a global carbon sink, essential for climate change mitigation efforts and the achievement of the Paris Agreement targets. This critical function also supports biodiversity and other ecosystem services. However, a significant gap in our understanding of marine carbon budgets is the fate of carbon exported from seaweed forests, the largest vegetated ecosystems along our coasts.</p>

<p>Our research has provided groundbreaking national and global estimates of particulate carbon export from seaweed forests to depths below 200 meters, revealing that this process accounts for 3-4% of the ocean’s carbon sink capacity. The study utilized sophisticated models to assess seaweed forest extent, production, decomposition, and the exchange of water between the continental shelf and the open ocean.</p>

<p><b>Key findings:</b></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Seaweed Carbon Export: On average, 15% of seaweed production is exported beyond the continental shelf. This translates to an estimated 56 teragrams of carbon per year (TgC yr−1), with a range between 10 and 170 TgC yr−1.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sequestration Potential: Of the exported carbon, it is estimated that 4 to 44 Tg of seaweed-derived carbon could be sequestered for up to 100 years at depths below 200 meters annually.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>These insights underscore the significant but previously underappreciated role of seaweed forests in carbon sequestration. Although the study did not account for shelf burial and dissolved and refractory carbon pathways, it highlights the substantial potential of seaweed as a natural carbon sink.</p>

<p><b>Implications for conservation and climate mitigation</b></p>

<p>Understanding the full extent of seaweed carbon sequestration is crucial for guiding conservation efforts, particularly as seaweed forests face global declines. Protecting and restoring these ecosystems could enhance their carbon sequestration potential, contributing to climate mitigation strategies.</p>

<p>This research underscores the importance of seaweed forests in the global carbon cycle. By continuing to investigate and understand the mechanisms behind seaweed carbon export and sequestration, we can better inform conservation policies and climate change mitigation efforts. Protecting these vital ecosystems is not only essential for biodiversity but also for sustaining their role as natural carbon sinks in our fight against climate change.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The coastal ocean plays a crucial role as a global carbon sink, essential for climate change mitigation efforts and the achievement of the Paris Agreement targets. This critical function also supports biodiversity and other ecosystem services. However, a significant gap in our understanding of marine carbon budgets is the fate of carbon exported from seaweed forests, the largest vegetated ecosystems along our coasts.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Ocean currents shaping genetic differentiation of marine forests</title><link href="/role-ocean-currents-marine-forests-differentiation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ocean currents shaping genetic differentiation of marine forests" /><published>2024-05-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/role-ocean-currents-marine-forests-differentiation/"><![CDATA[<p>The genetic diversity of marine forests arises from complex eco-evolutionary interactions. Our research focuses on the significant role that oceanographic connectivity—driven by water transport and dispersal—plays in shaping this diversity on a global scale.</p>

<p><b>Key findings: It’s all about connections</b></p>

<p>It turns out that ocean currents play a much bigger role than previously thought in shaping the genetic makeup of marine forests across the globe. These currents act as underwater highways, carrying propagules from one population to another.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Eco-Evolutionary Puzzle: We combined genetic data from nearly 700 seaweed populations with cutting-edge models of ocean currents. This allowed us to piece together the complex puzzle of how site-specific factors, ocean connectivity, and even rare long-distance dispersal events interact to shape genetic diversity.</li>
  <li>The 18.7% Surprise: Our research shows that almost one-fifth (18.7%) of the variation in genetic diversity across marine forests can be directly linked to the patterns of ocean circulation. This is a significant finding!</li>
  <li>Global Implications: This isn’t just about seaweed. Understanding how connected different populations are has major implications for marine conservation. It means we can better identify which areas to protect, ensuring that these vital ecosystems remain healthy and resilient in the face of climate change and other threats.</li>
</ol>

<p><br /></p>

<p><b>Why this matters?</b></p>

<p>Marine forests are like the underwater equivalent of rainforests – teeming with life and providing essential habitats for countless species. They also play a key role in capturing carbon and supporting fisheries. By understanding the drivers that shape their genetic diversity, we’re taking a big step towards safeguarding these precious ecosystems for future generations.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The genetic diversity of marine forests arises from complex eco-evolutionary interactions. Our research focuses on the significant role that oceanographic connectivity—driven by water transport and dispersal—plays in shaping this diversity on a global scale.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">A global dataset of demosponge distribution records</title><link href="/dataset-marine-sponges-distribution-records/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A global dataset of demosponge distribution records" /><published>2024-05-09T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-09T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dataset-marine-sponges-distribution-records/"><![CDATA[<p>Demosponges, a dominant group within the sponge phylum, play crucial roles in the health of our oceans. These organisms create intricate habitats for marine life and are integral to nutrient cycling in underwater ecosystems. Understanding their biodiversity and distribution is vital for ocean conservation, yet accurate datasets can be hard to come by.  Errors in species identification, location data, and inconsistent formatting across different sources often hinder reliable research.</p>

<p>Our team has addressed these challenges by developing a comprehensive, quality-controlled dataset focused specifically on Demospongiae occurrence records. We have aggregated data from multiple sources, carefully checked for errors, and cross-referenced records with expert knowledge on the expected geographic and depth ranges of each species. The dataset is formatted in the Darwin Core Standard, making it easy to use with a wide range of research tools.</p>

<p>This dataset offers marine scientists a powerful resource for investigating demosponge diversity patterns, including hotspots of species richness and unique species (endemism). It can also help predict how sponge populations might shift in response to climate change, guiding more effective conservation measures. We are committed to the principle of making research data openly accessible. By providing this dataset, we hope to advance marine science and our understanding of Earth’s precious oceans.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data" /><category term="Biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Demosponges, a dominant group within the sponge phylum, play crucial roles in the health of our oceans. These organisms create intricate habitats for marine life and are integral to nutrient cycling in underwater ecosystems. Understanding their biodiversity and distribution is vital for ocean conservation, yet accurate datasets can be hard to come by. Errors in species identification, location data, and inconsistent formatting across different sources often hinder reliable research.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Cryptic diversity in southern African kelp</title><link href="/cryptic-diversity-southern-africa/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cryptic diversity in southern African kelp" /><published>2024-04-19T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-19T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/cryptic-diversity-southern-africa/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Multidisciplinary estimates of connectivity and population structure suggest the use of multiple units for the conservation and management of meagre, Argyrosomus regius</title><link href="/multidisciplinary-estimates-connectivity-meagre/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multidisciplinary estimates of connectivity and population structure suggest the use of multiple units for the conservation and management of meagre, Argyrosomus regius" /><published>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/multidisciplinary-estimates-connectivity-meagre/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Trans-Arctic asymmetries, melting pots and weak species cohesion in the low-dispersal amphiboreal seaweed Fucus distichus</title><link href="/asymmetries-seaweed-fucus-distichus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trans-Arctic asymmetries, melting pots and weak species cohesion in the low-dispersal amphiboreal seaweed Fucus distichus" /><published>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/asymmetries-seaweed-fucus-distichus/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Incorporating physiological knowledge into correlative species distribution models minimizes bias introduced by the choice of calibration area</title><link href="/physiological-knowledge-distribution-models/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Incorporating physiological knowledge into correlative species distribution models minimizes bias introduced by the choice of calibration area" /><published>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/physiological-knowledge-distribution-models/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Climate change to reshape kelp forest diversity</title><link href="/climate-change-reshape-kelp-forest-diversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate change to reshape kelp forest diversity" /><published>2024-03-18T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-18T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/climate-change-reshape-kelp-forest-diversity/"><![CDATA[<p>Kelp forests, the vibrant underwater habitats found in temperate coastal regions, face a serious threat from climate change. Understanding how this shifting climate will alter kelp biodiversity and ecosystem health is essential, yet the full scope of potential changes remains unclear. This uncertainty hinders effective conservation and management, leaving these vital marine ecosystems vulnerable.</p>

<p>Our research team is addressing this knowledge gap. We’ve harnessed machine-learning models to project how climate change might affect the distribution and biodiversity of 105 different kelp species worldwide. Our models consider different climate scenarios, including a future where the Paris Agreement targets are met, and one with higher emissions. Our findings suggest that kelp species are likely to move towards the poles and into deeper waters as temperatures rise. The total area of suitable kelp habitat may decline by around 15%, with dramatic shifts in kelp communities occurring in the Arctic, Northern Pacific, Atlantic, and Australasia.  If emissions remain high, some regions may experience severe biodiversity loss with important kelp species disappearing completely, impacting the overall health of the ecosystem.</p>

<p>This research offers a stark warning about the future of kelp forests, but it also provides a vital tool. Policymakers and conservationists can use our data to identify the areas where kelp biodiversity is most vulnerable, prioritize efforts to protect and possibly restore the most critical kelp habitats, and understand how marine ecosystems might change so conservation strategies can be adapted accordingly.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Climate change threatens to disrupt these underwater havens, but we can take action. Our new research provides a roadmap for conservation, highlighting regions most at risk and where protection efforts are most needed.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Range map data of ecosystem structuring species under global climate change</title><link href="/range-map-ecosystem-structuring-species-global-climate-change/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Range map data of ecosystem structuring species under global climate change" /><published>2024-03-08T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-08T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/range-map-ecosystem-structuring-species-global-climate-change/"><![CDATA[<p>Understanding how climate change will reshape the distribution of marine species is essential for developing effective conservation strategies. Yet, many crucial species – those that form essential underwater habitats – have been overlooked in existing data. Additionally, outdated climate models have hampered accurate projections of how these species might fare in the long term.</p>

<p>Our team addresses these issues by providing detailed range maps for 980 marine species critical to ocean health, including seagrasses, kelps, fucoids, and cold-water corals. These maps cover both current distributions (2010-2020) and future scenarios (2090-2100).  Importantly, our projections use the latest climate models, from low emission scenarios outlined in the Paris Agreement to higher emission possibilities, giving a realistic range of potential outcomes.</p>

<p>Building these maps involved advanced machine learning algorithms, the most comprehensive datasets available, and careful quality control.  This focus on accuracy means our maps offer a powerful tool for policymakers and conservationists, offering insights into:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Changing “Hotspots”: Where marine biodiversity might increase or decrease.</li>
  <li>Vulnerable Habitats: Areas likely to experience the greatest shifts in species distribution.</li>
  <li>Conservation Planning: How to protect the most critical ecosystems as the climate changes.</li>
</ol>

<p>Our commitment is to provide scientifically rigorous data that can underpin effective ocean conservation and ensure the resilience of these vital marine environments.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data" /><category term="Biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding how climate change will reshape the distribution of marine species is essential for developing effective conservation strategies. Yet, many crucial species – those that form essential underwater habitats – have been overlooked in existing data. Additionally, outdated climate models have hampered accurate projections of how these species might fare in the long term.]]></summary></entry></feed>