<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-10T13:08:02+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">A global dataset of demosponge distribution records</title><link href="/dataset-marine-sponges-distribution-records/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A global dataset of demosponge distribution records" /><published>2024-05-09T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-09T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dataset-marine-sponges-distribution-records/"><![CDATA[<p>Demosponges, a dominant group within the sponge phylum, play crucial roles in the health of our oceans. These organisms create intricate habitats for marine life and are integral to nutrient cycling in underwater ecosystems. Understanding their biodiversity and distribution is vital for ocean conservation, yet accurate datasets can be hard to come by.  Errors in species identification, location data, and inconsistent formatting across different sources often hinder reliable research.</p>

<p>Our team has addressed these challenges by developing a comprehensive, quality-controlled dataset focused specifically on Demospongiae occurrence records. We have aggregated data from multiple sources, carefully checked for errors, and cross-referenced records with expert knowledge on the expected geographic and depth ranges of each species. The dataset is formatted in the Darwin Core Standard, making it easy to use with a wide range of research tools.</p>

<p>This dataset offers marine scientists a powerful resource for investigating demosponge diversity patterns, including hotspots of species richness and unique species (endemism). It can also help predict how sponge populations might shift in response to climate change, guiding more effective conservation measures. We are committed to the principle of making research data openly accessible. By providing this dataset, we hope to advance marine science and our understanding of Earth’s precious oceans.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data" /><category term="Biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Demosponges, a dominant group within the sponge phylum, play crucial roles in the health of our oceans. These organisms create intricate habitats for marine life and are integral to nutrient cycling in underwater ecosystems. Understanding their biodiversity and distribution is vital for ocean conservation, yet accurate datasets can be hard to come by. Errors in species identification, location data, and inconsistent formatting across different sources often hinder reliable research.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Climate change to reshape kelp forest diversity</title><link href="/climate-change-reshape-kelp-forest-diversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate change to reshape kelp forest diversity" /><published>2024-03-18T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-18T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/climate-change-reshape-kelp-forest-diversity/"><![CDATA[<p>Kelp forests, the vibrant underwater habitats found in temperate coastal regions, face a serious threat from climate change. Understanding how this shifting climate will alter kelp biodiversity and ecosystem health is essential, yet the full scope of potential changes remains unclear. This uncertainty hinders effective conservation and management, leaving these vital marine ecosystems vulnerable.</p>

<p>Our research team is addressing this knowledge gap. We’ve harnessed machine-learning models to project how climate change might affect the distribution and biodiversity of 105 different kelp species worldwide. Our models consider different climate scenarios, including a future where the Paris Agreement targets are met, and one with higher emissions. Our findings suggest that kelp species are likely to move towards the poles and into deeper waters as temperatures rise. The total area of suitable kelp habitat may decline by around 15%, with dramatic shifts in kelp communities occurring in the Arctic, Northern Pacific, Atlantic, and Australasia.  If emissions remain high, some regions may experience severe biodiversity loss with important kelp species disappearing completely, impacting the overall health of the ecosystem.</p>

<p>This research offers a stark warning about the future of kelp forests, but it also provides a vital tool. Policymakers and conservationists can use our data to identify the areas where kelp biodiversity is most vulnerable, prioritize efforts to protect and possibly restore the most critical kelp habitats, and understand how marine ecosystems might change so conservation strategies can be adapted accordingly.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Climate change threatens to disrupt these underwater havens, but we can take action. Our new research provides a roadmap for conservation, highlighting regions most at risk and where protection efforts are most needed.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Range map data of ecosystem structuring species under global climate change</title><link href="/range-map-ecosystem-structuring-species-global-climate-change/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Range map data of ecosystem structuring species under global climate change" /><published>2024-03-08T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-08T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/range-map-ecosystem-structuring-species-global-climate-change/"><![CDATA[<p>Understanding how climate change will reshape the distribution of marine species is essential for developing effective conservation strategies. Yet, many crucial species – those that form essential underwater habitats – have been overlooked in existing data. Additionally, outdated climate models have hampered accurate projections of how these species might fare in the long term.</p>

<p>Our team addresses these issues by providing detailed range maps for 980 marine species critical to ocean health, including seagrasses, kelps, fucoids, and cold-water corals. These maps cover both current distributions (2010-2020) and future scenarios (2090-2100).  Importantly, our projections use the latest climate models, from low emission scenarios outlined in the Paris Agreement to higher emission possibilities, giving a realistic range of potential outcomes.</p>

<p>Building these maps involved advanced machine learning algorithms, the most comprehensive datasets available, and careful quality control.  This focus on accuracy means our maps offer a powerful tool for policymakers and conservationists, offering insights into:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Changing “Hotspots”: Where marine biodiversity might increase or decrease.</li>
  <li>Vulnerable Habitats: Areas likely to experience the greatest shifts in species distribution.</li>
  <li>Conservation Planning: How to protect the most critical ecosystems as the climate changes.</li>
</ol>

<p>Our commitment is to provide scientifically rigorous data that can underpin effective ocean conservation and ensure the resilience of these vital marine environments.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data" /><category term="Biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding how climate change will reshape the distribution of marine species is essential for developing effective conservation strategies. Yet, many crucial species – those that form essential underwater habitats – have been overlooked in existing data. Additionally, outdated climate models have hampered accurate projections of how these species might fare in the long term.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Heatwaves are more intense and persist longer in deeper waters</title><link href="/marine-heatwaves-more-intense-persist-longer-deeper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heatwaves are more intense and persist longer in deeper waters" /><published>2023-09-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-09-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-heatwaves-more-intense-persist-longer-deeper/"><![CDATA[<p>The world’s oceans have reached their highest recorded temperatures in 2023, and it is forecasted that the intensity, duration, and frequency of marine heatwaves - defined as periods of elevated sea temperatures lasting at least five days - will continue to increase throughout the century. Until now, the impacts and projections of these events have focused on the sea surface, however, localized observations suggest that marine heatwaves can occur below the surface and persist for years. The rising of ocean temperatures has profound consequences for the planet’s geochemical and biological systems, directly affecting marine flora and fauna, and therefore the resources humans depend on.</p>

<p>Using global-level sea temperature observations and reanalysis data, our reseearch group estimated the duration and intensity of marine heatwaves from 1993 to 2019 at depths down to 2,000 meters. The research published in the journal Nature Climate Change, shows that the highest intensity of marine heatwaves is not at the surface but in the subsurface, specifically between 50 and 250 meters deep. “Against our initial expectations, we found that marine heat waves are more intense below the surface, and their duration can last up to double, when compared to the surface,” notes Eliza Fragkopoulou, the leading author of the study.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/figure2-b.webp" alt="Heatwaves are intense and persist in deeper waters" style="max-height: 625px;" /></p>

<p>We combined these findings with data on marine species ranges, and predicted that subsurface biodiversity could be at risk due to higher cumulative intensity (an indicator of thermal stress) in the first 250 meters. Jorge Assis, who led the research explains: “Across the globe, we identified regions of higher risk for marine biodiversity, including significant portions of the Indian and North Atlantic Oceans, where high cumulative heatwave intensity coincides with areas of predicted high species sensitivity to thermal stress. What we’ve discovered is that beyond readily detectable surface effects, such as losses of ecosystem structuring species of mangrove and kelp forests and coral reefs, marine heatwaves can have profound effects on deeper biodiversity, down to 250 meters.”</p>

<p>A noteworthy aspect of this study is the extension of temperature changes from the surface to greatest depths. However, temperature data from deep areas should be taken with caution, especially data prior to 2004, when a more reliable measurement system was implemented. In addition to temperature increases, other changes in ocean conditions need consideration. Temperature extremes are expected to redistribute marine species from the surface to the deep ocean, however, additional constrains, such as low oxygen regions, may hinder such redistribution, with unpredictable consequences. In this context, additional monitoring of marine biodiversity under ongoing extreme climate conditions is needed to better understand and predict their effects.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Global analysis shows deep marine biodiversity facing higher risk of exposure to the cumulative effect of intense and prolonged heatwave events.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Biodiversity database of West Africa</title><link href="/biodiversity-database-west-africa/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Biodiversity database of West Africa" /><published>2023-09-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-09-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/biodiversity-database-west-africa/"><![CDATA[<p>The biodiversity database of West Africa is a service provided to Project Marafrica with the main aim of developing a stable, straightforward and flexible framework for sharing biodiversity data, making publicly available all the biodiversity records of the Banc D’Arguin National Park and the Bijagós archipelago to inform managers, scientists and the general public.</p>

<div style="padding: 20px" class="border-radius-05 bg-gray font-family-secondary font-small text-dark">
Explore the webpage at <a target="_black" href="https://www.marafrica.net">https://www.marafrica.net</a>.
</div>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/project-9-3.png" alt="Graphical interface" style="max-height: 525px;" /></p>

<p>Project Marafrica is a network for monitoring, integrating and assessing marine biodiversity data along the west africa to understand, predict and mitigate climatic / oceanographic changes. It is funded by the Aga-Khan Foundation and FCT-Portugal and Project STM - Survi des Tortues Marines.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A database structured under Darwin Core standards, offering a stable, straightforward and flexible framework for sharing biodiversity data to managers, scientists and the general public.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Oceanographic connectivity explains the intra-specific diversity of mangrove forests</title><link href="/oceanographic-connectivity-explains-diversity-mangrove-forests/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Oceanographic connectivity explains the intra-specific diversity of mangrove forests" /><published>2023-08-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-08-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/oceanographic-connectivity-explains-diversity-mangrove-forests/"><![CDATA[<p>Our research group has recently conducted a groundbreaking study that sheds light on the critical role of ocean currents in shaping the genetic diversity of mangroves. Mangrove ecosystems are renowned for their ecological importance, providing valuable services like carbon sequestration, coastal protection, and habitats for various species.</p>

<p>Traditionally, scientists attributed regional differences in mangrove populations and species to historical climate changes, ongoing climate shifts, and human disturbances. However, this study reveals that ocean currents are equally pivotal factors shaping the dynamics of mangrove biodiversity and conservation.</p>

<p>Using state-of-the-art biophysical modeling techniques, we assessed the extent to which mangrove populations are interconnected via ocean currents. These estimates were then validated using genetic data from diverse mangrove species across the globe. The study challenges conventional approaches that rely solely on geographic distances, instead underscoring the critical role that ocean currents play in connecting mangrove populations over vast distances, sometimes spanning thousands of kilometers.</p>

<p>Our lead authors, Lidiane Gouvêa and Jorge Assis, emphasize the far-reaching implications of these findings. They point out that future alterations in ocean current patterns could lead to the isolation and divergence of mangrove populations. Over time, this could result in reduced biodiversity, increased risks of regional extinctions, and direct consequences for the native communities in tropical countries that rely on the species within mangrove forests.</p>

<p>In summary, our research group’s study highlights how ocean currents significantly influence the genetic diversity of mangroves. It underscores the urgent need for the preservation of these vital ecosystems and the species dependent on them.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The crucial role of ocean currents in shaping mangrove genetic diversity, challenging previous assumptions and emphasizing the importance of preserving these ecosystems.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Modeling aquaculture in a changing climate</title><link href="/modeling-aquaculture-changing-climate/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modeling aquaculture in a changing climate" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/modeling-aquaculture-changing-climate/"><![CDATA[<p>Aquaculture is currently the fastest-growing food production industry and accounts for more than half of seafood production. This rapid growth is projected to double by 2050 to meet the rising demand for seafood, which is unlikely to be met by wild capture fisheries as many species are fully or overexploited and will be further limited by climate change impacts. However, marine aquaculture relies on environmental factors which will also experience shifts due to climate change. Understanding how these shifts will affect aquaculture species and regions will enable the industry to plan for and adapt to a changing marine environment.</p>

<p>This research project will take a modeling approach to examine how climate change will impact the spatio-temporal distributions of marine aquaculture species and global regions of marine aquaculture development. Additionally, this project will investigate the impacts climate change and species movement will have on the socio-economic factors limiting the growth of the industry including production yield, marine areas zoned for aquaculture, industry resource needs, and government investment. The culmination of this project will be an index of aquaculture suitability to aid governments and the aquaculture industry in establishing management techniques to facilitate the continued growth and sustainability of aquaculture in a changing climate.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A modeling approach to examine how climate change will impact marine aquaculture species and regions of marine aquaculture development.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Consequences of future climate change for marine forests gene pools</title><link href="/consequences-future-climate-genes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Consequences of future climate change for marine forests gene pools" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/consequences-future-climate-genes/"><![CDATA[<p>Climate change is driving the redistribution of marine biodiversity, altering the stability and functionality of marine ecosystems. Its impacts are particularly striking for marine forest species, the structural basis of coastal ecosystems, with cascading effects that reduce local biodiversity and disrupt ecosystem services. For the low dispersive and sessile marine forest species, the key to their persistence through changing climates may be held in their ability to adapt to new conditions. Evolutionary theory supports that populations with higher genetic diversity show higher adaptive capacities and plasticity, increasing their probabilities of persistence. Thus, identifying the drivers of genetic diversity and the populations holding higher diversity is crucial for conservation and effective management.</p>

<p>At the ecosystem level, species richness and endemism are fundamental metrics of biodiversity and are used as indicators of high conservation value. Yet, such biodiversity estimates and their drivers are limited for the marine environment and especially for marine forest species, precluding effective conservation and prioritization.</p>

<p>Understanding how biodiversity patterns, from genes to ecosystems, have been shaped through fluctuating past climates, can help us hindcast future patterns that can inform conservation strategies. This project aims to study the drivers of marine forest biodiversity, from genes to ecosystems, and provide stakeholders and scientists with quantitative measurements of present-day gene diversity, species richness and endemicity, as well as future estimates, in the form of climate change impact assessments.</p>

<p>The outcomes of our analyses will provide quantitative measures of marine forest biodiversity for the present day and the future, which could be used to guide political decisions for effective conservation and management measures.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A project aimed at investigating the effects of climate change on key marine forest species, such as kelp, fucoids and cold-water corals.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">High-performance computing projects climate change impacts on biodiversity</title><link href="/high-performance-computing-projects-climate-change-biodiversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="High-performance computing projects climate change impacts on biodiversity" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/high-performance-computing-projects-climate-change-biodiversity/"><![CDATA[<p>The project embarks on a mission to understand the profound impact of climate change on marine biodiversity at a global scale. Empirical evidence has shown significant shifts in the distribution and behavior of marine life due to climate change, with species moving poleward, equatorward, and changing depths. As greenhouse gas emissions continue to rise, the vulnerability of biodiversity escalates, potentially leading to substantial losses, from individual genes to entire ecosystems. However, traditional assessments of these impacts often fall short, relying on climate velocity indicators that consider temperature alone, neglecting other critical factors like oxygen levels, pH, and primary productivity. Additionally, they overlook the role of oceanographic connectivity, which can restrict species’ ability to adapt to shifting environmental conditions, particularly for species with limited dispersal capabilities.</p>

<p>Our research team is poised to address these challenges comprehensively. We will employ high-performance computing and advanced algorithms to develop an innovative approach that combines climate change exposure assessments with oceanographic connectivity estimates. This approach will help us identify regions where marine biodiversity faces potential extinction, regions of persistence, and ocean-accessible climatic corridors.</p>

<p>Experiments will span from the year 2020 to 2100, examining various scenarios of global change. We will consider multiple environmental predictors, including sea surface temperature, oxygen levels, productivity, and pH, while factoring in the direction and intensity of ocean currents. By identifying analogs in climate conditions through time, we aim to pinpoint sites where conditions will resemble those of current habitats. Oceanographic connectivity will be incorporated into our analysis, allowing us to account for the dispersal limitations of marine species. We will use advanced mathematical techniques, including sigma dissimilarity and anisotropic resistance surfaces, parameterized with ocean current data.</p>

<p>In summary, our project aims to provide valuable insights into the future of marine biodiversity under the influence of climate change. Our findings will contribute to informed conservation and management policies, aligning with the Sustainable Development Goals 9, 13, and 14 of the 2030 Agenda and aiding the IPCC’s impact assessments.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Experiments will identify regions of extinction, persistence and ocean-accessible, climatic corridors for biodiversity.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Marine Protected Areas Europe</title><link href="/marine-protected-areas-europe-horizon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Marine Protected Areas Europe" /><published>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-protected-areas-europe-horizon/"><![CDATA[<p>MPA Europe uses a holistic range of measures that include the range of biodiversity from species to ecosystems, including habitats, areas will be prioritised using systematic conservation planning software. This enables alternative weighting of variables and multiple scenarios and thus support wider marine spatial planning.</p>

<p>The project adopts an interdisciplinary approach, employing comprehensive measures of biodiversity that encompass variation both within and between species and ecosystems. It also considers various environmental variables, carbon cycle dynamics, and climate change scenarios. Our team consists of experts in marine biology, taxonomy, ecology, oceanography, biogeochemistry, biogeography, MPA network design, benthic habitat mapping, carbon dynamics, as well as species distribution and climate modeling.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/MPAinfographic-1500x844.png" alt="Graphical interface" style="max-height: 925px;" /></p>

<p>The project is ambitious in committing to achieve several firsts in terms of products based on new data and analyses: (1) Maps of an optimal MPA network in European seas prioritised for biodiversity protection and blue carbon benefits; (2) Maps of species richness in European seas based on multiple indicators, including actual observed data, statistical estimators, and modelled geographic range maps; (3) Potential geographic distributions of important biogenic habitats in European seas.</p>

<div style="padding: 20px" class="border-radius-05 bg-gray font-family-secondary font-small text-dark">
Explore the webpage of the project at <a target="_black" href="https://mpa-europe.eu/">www.mpa-europe.eu</a>.
</div>

<p><br />
MPA Europe project has been approved under HORIZON-CL6-2021-BIODIV-01-12 — Improved science based maritime spatial planning and identification of marine protected areas.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[MPA Europe will map the optimal locations for marine protected areas in European seas.]]></summary></entry></feed>