<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-24T17:07:02+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BiodiversityDataScience</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Cold‐Water coral redistribution under climate change</title><link href="/coral-redistribution-under-climate-change-biodiversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cold‐Water coral redistribution under climate change" /><published>2025-06-25T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-25T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/coral-redistribution-under-climate-change-biodiversity/"><![CDATA[<p>Cold-water corals (CWCs) are critical ecosystem-structuring species that provide essential services, from continental shelves to abyssal depths. They create complex, three-dimensional habitats, acting as feeding, breeding, and nursery grounds for a wide range of commercially important fish and invertebrates. Their future, however, is heavily dependent on the planet’s climate trajectory.</p>

<h5>The critical knowledge gap</h5>

<p>Despite their immense ecological importance, knowledge of the global distribution, diversity patterns, and overall vulnerability of cold-water corals to climate change remains severely limited. This knowledge gap constrains effective, large-scale conservation strategies, particularly the design of robust Marine Protected Areas (MPAs) needed to meet global protection targets.</p>

<h5>Our main approach</h5>

<p>We conducted the most extensive global assessment of CWC biogeography to date, analyzing 741 species spanning six major taxonomic groups. We used this data to predict species distributions under present-day conditions and project future shifts under two contrasting end-of-century climate scenarios: the low-emission SSP1-1.9 (aligned with the Paris Agreement) and the high-emission SSP3-7.0. Our analysis was based on three pillars:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Mapping global species richness and identifying biodiversity hotspots.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Delineating ten distinct cold-water coral bioregions based on species co-occurrence.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Quantifying projected shifts in species richness, community turnover, and identifying climate refugia.</p>

<h5>Technological challenge: how we tackle the study</h5>

<p>To accurately model the distribution of these complex, low-dispersal organisms, we employed an ensemble of high-performance machine learning Species Distribution Models (SDMs), including Boosted Regression Trees (BRT), Adaptive Boosting (AdaBoost), and Extreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost). Our key methodological innovations included:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Monotonicity constraints: We applied ecological constraints to the models (e.g., assuming higher maximum temperature has a negative effect), ensuring the predictions were biologically realistic and reducing the risk of overfitting.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Dispersal constraints: To account for the slow growth rates and limited dispersal of CWCs, we clipped distribution maps using a maximum dispersal constraint of 200km, which significantly reduced overprediction.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Bioregion validation: We used k-means clustering to delineate the ten bioregions and statistically confirmed their distinctiveness using Analysis of Similarities (ANOSIM).</p>

<h5>The main finding</h5>

<p>Our results showed major biodiversity hotspots in the Gulf of Mexico and the Caribbean Sea, and delineated ten distinct bioregions, each with varying species richness, depth distribution patterns, and generally low levels of endemicity.</p>

<div class="border-radius-10 margin-top-20" style="background-color: white; padding: 10px; max-width: 900px; margin-bottom: 10px">
<img src="/assets/images/posts/gcb70563-fig-0002-m.webp" style="max-width: 880px;" />
</div>
<p>Fig. Present-day species richness distribution for 741 species of cold-water corals.</p>

<p>While the global extent of suitable CWC habitat is projected to persist, species-level redistributions will drive dramatic change, with the magnitude strongly tied to emission levels. We identified the Gulf of Mexico and the Caribbean Sea as major present-day biodiversity hotspots. Under the high-emission scenario (SSP3-7.0), we projected:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Widespread poleward and depth shifts, with average species distribution projected to deepen by 26.0m.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Significant biodiversity loss in shallow and low-latitude regions, with the Central Western Atlantic projected to lose up to 66 species.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Richness gains primarily concentrated in deeper offshore areas and the Arctic, indicating potential but fragile new habitats.</p>

<div class="border-radius-10 margin-top-20" style="background-color: white; padding: 10px; max-width: 900px; margin-bottom: 10px">
<img src="/assets/images/posts/gcb70563-fig-0004-m.webp" style="max-width: 880px;" />
</div>
<p>Fig. Projected end-of-century changes under SSP1-1.9 and SSP3-7.0 in (a, b) species richness, (c, d) climate refugia, and (e, f) community turnover of cold-water corals. Climate refugia represent the fraction of species predicted to retain suitable habitat (0 = none persist; 1 = all persist). Turnover ranges from 0 (no change in species composition) to 1 (complete replacement). Areas with no species present are shown in white.</p>

<h5>Main implications for conservation and management of biodiversity</h5>

<p>Our findings underscore the urgent need for global climate action aligned with the Paris Agreement. The study provides an actionable framework to support the UN 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development and the post-2020 Global Biodiversity Framework.</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Prioritizing Conservation: We pinpoint biodiversity hotspots and emerging climate refugia, offering crucial guidance for the strategic designation of new MPAs.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Addressing Synergistic Risks: Our data highlights the amplification of risks in regions like the Gulf of Mexico, where a global CWC hotspot overlaps with major oil and gas extraction zones, requiring immediate, targeted mitigation.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Spatially Explicit Strategies: The ten newly defined bioregions, structured primarily by depth and species composition, enable conservation efforts to be tailored precisely to the unique assemblage of species found in each region.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="climate change" /><category term="conservation" /><category term="biodiversity" /><category term="paris agreement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Climate change will force cold-water corals to shift poleward and deeper, causing significant biodiversity loss in shallow, low-latitude regions unless global emissions are drastically reduced.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mapping global shipless areas and conflict with biodiversity</title><link href="/global-shipless-areas-conflict-with-biodiversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping global shipless areas and conflict with biodiversity" /><published>2025-04-25T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-04-25T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/global-shipless-areas-conflict-with-biodiversity/"><![CDATA[<h5>The knowledge gap</h5>
<p>Despite clear evidence that shipping activity—through vessel collisions, noise pollution, and disturbance—severely impacts marine megafauna like cetaceans, sea turtles, pinnipeds, and seabirds, there was no comprehensive global map to guide conservation efforts. We lacked the vital knowledge to distinguish between undisturbed biodiversity refuges and high-risk conflict zones at a planetary scale.</p>

<h5>Main approach</h5>
<p>We conducted a global assessment by overlaying two critical layers: a composite measure of species richness for the four vulnerable faunal groups and vessel density derived from Automatic Identification System (AIS) data. By classifying both metrics into terciles (low, medium, high), we were able to define two new conservation categories:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Priority Preservation Areas (PPAs): Regions of high species richness overlapping with low or minimal shipping activity (biodiversity refuges).<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Priority Mitigation Areas (PMAs): Regions of high species richness overlapping with high shipping density (high-risk conflict zones)</p>

<h5>Technological challenge - how we tackle the study</h5>
<p>The core challenge was translating vast, continuous streams of global maritime traffic (AIS data) and highly dynamic species distribution models (AquaMaps and BirdLife) into a single, actionable risk assessment framework. We used a bivariate mapping approach in R to synthesize these complex datasets, enabling us to quantify the interplay between biodiversity value and potential impact risk across every marine grid cell, making the findings globally consistent and scalable.</p>

<h5>Main finding</h5>
<p>Our maps reveal that biodiversity is concentrated in two major zones. PPAs—our ocean’s last large, undisturbed refuges—are predominantly found in the remote, high southern latitudes, near Antarctica. Conversely, PMAs are clustered along coastlines and in critical trans-oceanic passages, especially in the mid-Pacific, southern Indian Ocean, and South Atlantic. Crucially, we found that existing Marine Protected Areas (MPAs) are currently falling short: they cover only 15.2% of PPAs and 16.2% of PMAs, leaving vast priority areas unprotected or unmanaged.</p>

<h5>Main implications for conservation and management of biodiversity</h5>
<p>These findings provide a clear roadmap for achieving global marine conservation goals, including the UN 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development and the $30 \times 30$ target. We need a dual-strategy approach to marine spatial planning:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Preserve: Immediately designate the identified PPAs as new MPAs or equivalent conservation measures to safeguard these essential, shipless biodiversity refuges before future traffic routes encroach.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Mitigate: Implement targeted shipping management strategies in PMAs, such as mandatory vessel speed reductions to minimize lethal collisions and noise pollution, and dynamic traffic rerouting to avoid seasonal biodiversity hotspots.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Govern: Use this framework to inform international policies on the High Seas, helping countries and organizations balance vital maritime trade with the urgent need to protect vulnerable marine ecosystems.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="conservation" /><category term="biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The global maritime industry, the lifeblood of our modern economy, is rapidly expanding, but its growing footprint poses an immense, quantified threat to the ocean's largest inhabitants.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html"></title><link href="/marine-forever-5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2025-03-10T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-10T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-forever-5/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="archived" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html"></title><link href="/marine-forever-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2025-03-10T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-10T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-forever-3/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="archived" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html"></title><link href="/marine-forever-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2025-03-01T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-forever-2/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="archived" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html"></title><link href="/marine-forever-211/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2025-03-01T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-forever-211/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="archived" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Global map of genetic diversity of marine forests</title><link href="/global-map-genetic-diversity-marine-forests/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Global map of genetic diversity of marine forests" /><published>2025-02-25T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-25T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/global-map-genetic-diversity-marine-forests/"><![CDATA[<p>Marine forests, often called the “rainforests of the sea,” are vital ecosystems, but how do we effectively protect their evolutionary potential against a changing climate? Our new research uses artificial intelligence to look back 20,000 years, revealing that the genetic strength of today’s kelp and seaweed is a direct inheritance from the Ice Age. This finding fundamentally changes how we must approach global marine conservation.</p>

<h5>Knowledge gap</h5>
<p>While we know that intraspecific genetic diversity is crucial for species survival and adaptation, global estimates for this diversity remain limited, especially for low-dispersive marine species like the brown macroalgae that form these expansive marine forests. Existing studies are fragmented, leaving a significant gap in our biogeographic understanding of their long-term evolutionary dynamics.</p>

<h5>Main approach</h5>
<p>To close this gap, we developed a unified machine learning model grounded in the niche centroid hypothesis. This hypothesis suggests that genetic diversity peaks where environmental conditions are optimal (the niche centroid) and declines towards the periphery. Critically, our model integrated environmental conditions from two time periods: contemporary times (present day) and the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM), approximately 20,000 years ago.</p>

<h5>Technological challenge - how we tackle the study</h5>
<p>The main challenge was building a predictive model robust enough to reconcile historical, present, and species-specific data. We tackled this by employing Boosted Regression Trees (BRT), a powerful machine-learning algorithm. This model was trained on genetic data from 29 brown macroalgae species and then applied to the distribution range maps of 280 marine forest species globally. This allowed us to predict and map genetic diversity across all oceans for the first time.</p>

<h5>Main finding</h5>
<p>Our models show that past climate conditions (LGM) have more than double the impact on observed genetic diversity levels than contemporary conditions. Genetic diversity is highest in regions that served as climatic refugia—areas where optimal conditions persisted even during the Ice Age. These hotspots of high genetic diversity align strongly with areas of high species richness.</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Past climate conditions emerged as the key driver, explaining significantly more genetic variability than contemporary conditions.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Genetic diversity peaks at the niche centroid distance when conditions were optimal during the LGM, confirming long-term persistence is a diversity driver.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Global hotspots of genetic diversity were mapped, notably in the north-eastern Pacific, north-eastern Atlantic, and the south coast of Australia.</p>

<h5>Main implications</h5>
<p>This baseline information is timely and critical for meeting the goals of the UN 2030 Agenda and the Post-2020 Global Biodiversity Framework. The high-resolution maps of genetic diversity hotspots can be used to:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Guide spatial conservation prioritization and the strategic implementation of Marine Protected Areas (MPAs) to safeguard rich gene pools.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Enhance restoration efforts by selecting genetically rich and non-divergent donor populations, increasing the likelihood of long-term restoration success.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Identify custodian countries (e.g., the United States, Norway, and Australia) that bear an increased responsibility for conserving these major genetic diversity reservoirs.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="machine learning" /><category term="macroecology" /><category term="biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Past climate conditions are main drivers shaping the genetic diversity of global marine forests, providing key conservation insights.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Projected climate change threaten European Seahorses</title><link href="/climate-change-threaten-european-seahorses-conservation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Projected climate change threaten European Seahorses" /><published>2025-02-25T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-25T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/climate-change-threaten-european-seahorses-conservation/"><![CDATA[<h5>The knowledge gap</h5>

<p>Climate change models often predict a simple poleward shift for marine life, assuming species can freely reach new suitable areas. For species with naturally low mobility, such as seahorses, this assumption is deeply flawed. We needed to understand how oceanographic connectivity—the ability of ocean currents to carry juveniles or rafting adults—interacts with climate-driven habitat shifts across their range.</p>

<h5>The main approach</h5>

<p>To address this, we integrated two powerful computational frameworks. First, we used Ensemble Species Distribution Modelling (ESDM) under high- and low-emission scenarios (SSP5 and SSP2) to map where suitable seahorse habitat will be in 2100. Second, we coupled this with a state-of-the-art biophysical model to simulate two realistic dispersal pathways: short pelagic drifting (14 days) and longer passive rafting (100 days).</p>

<h5>Technological challenge: how we tackle the study</h5>

<p>The core challenge was linking predictive habitat maps with real-world ocean current simulations. We utilized coastalNet, a biophysical model, to calculate multi-generational dispersal estimates. This graph-theoretical approach allowed us to see which newly-suitable northern areas could actually be reached by seahorses originating from current populations, effectively turning an ‘unlimited movement’ prediction into a ‘connectivity-constrained’ reality.</p>

<div class="image-placeholder"></div>

<h5>The main finding</h5>

<p>The incorporation of dispersal ability radically changed the forecast, revealing greater conservation risk than previously estimated:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Hippocampus guttulatus is projected to experience severe habitat contraction (up to 45% loss under high-emission scenarios), rather than the predicted expansion seen in standard models.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Hippocampus hippocampus still shows limited range expansion (+8% to +12%), but this is significantly less than the 17% expansion predicted by models that ignore dispersal limits.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Both species face severe losses across the southern distribution, particularly in the Mediterranean and North Africa, where the worst-case scenario (SSP5) projected over 80% and 50% loss for H. guttulatus and H. hippocampus, respectively.</p>

<h5>Main implications for conservation and management of biodiversity</h5>

<p>This research provides essential, grounded data for the UN 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, specifically SDG 14 (Life Below Water). The findings necessitate an immediate shift in conservation strategy:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Prioritize climate refugia: We must strengthen protection measures in areas projected to remain stable, such as the North Sea, the Bay of Biscay, and parts of the northern Iberian Atlantic Coast, especially under the lower-emission SSP2 scenario.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Mitigate local stressors: For isolated, vulnerable populations (e.g., in the Mediterranean’s Thau Lagoon), addressing localized threats like pollution, dredging, and destructive fishing is paramount, as they cannot relocate to escape climate change.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Spatial planning: Conservation efforts must now integrate oceanographic connectivity to identify and safeguard corridors necessary for future range shifts, ensuring that new suitable habitats are reachable.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="climate change" /><category term="conservation" /><category term="biodiversity" /><category term="paris agreement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Data science models show limited dispersal severely restricts seahorse adaptation to climate change, leading to major habitat contraction.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trophic convergence of marine vertebrate communities</title><link href="/trophic-convergence-marine-vertebrate-communities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trophic convergence of marine vertebrate communities" /><published>2025-01-25T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-25T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/trophic-convergence-marine-vertebrate-communities/"><![CDATA[<p>What if the marine ecosystems of the Arctic and the Southern Ocean, though vastly separated, function in the same fundamental way? Our new paper in PNAS shows that across the world’s oceans, species with completely different evolutionary histories are converging on the same feeding strategies.</p>

<p>We’ve used cutting-edge machine learning to reveal a new biogeography for the sea, one based not on who lives where, but on how species eat.</p>

<h5>Knowledge gap</h5>

<p>Traditional marine biogeography focuses heavily on endemism and geographical isolation to define ocean regions. While this provides valuable insights into evolutionary history, it often overlooks how ongoing ecological pressures shape the way communities actually function.</p>

<p>The fundamental question was: Does the ocean’s vast, fluid nature—which allows for easier dispersal compared to terrestrial environments—prevent a robust convergence of feeding strategies at a global scale? Could functionally analogous communities exist far apart?</p>

<h5>Main approach</h5>

<p>To address this, we performed a global-scale regionalization of the ocean based entirely on the trophic structure of marine vertebrate communities (fish, mammals, reptiles, and seabirds).</p>

<p>We analyzed comprehensive dietary data for 5,569 species to see how they organize into functional groups, or trophic guilds, and how the presence and richness of these guilds vary across the entire global ocean in over 668,000 grid cells.</p>

<h5>Technological challenge - how we tackle the study</h5>

<p>Mobilizing and analyzing a unified dataset of this scale required a robust, multi-stage machine learning framework.</p>

<p>We utilized:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Unsupervised Clustering: We used k-modes clustering to classify all 5,569 species into eleven core trophic guilds based on their complex dietary preferences.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Fuzzy Clustering (AMDi): We mapped the global distribution of guilds and used fuzzy c-means clustering to objectively identify the emergent and distinct trophic communities (TCs).<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Predictive Modeling: We trained powerful algorithms like Random Forests and Evolutionary Classification Trees to identify the key environmental variables—like temperature, depth, and salinity—that govern the spatial distribution of these TCs.</p>

<h5>Main finding</h5>

<p>We discovered six distinct types of trophic communities (TC1 through TC6) emerging consistently across the global ocean.</p>

<p>Crucially, communities that are geographically distant and composed of species from different evolutionary lineages often converge into the same functional type when they share similar environmental conditions. This functional convergence is overwhelmingly dictated by:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Temperature: As temperatures decrease toward the poles, the overall trophic complexity (the variety of feeding strategies) generally decreases.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Depth: Shallower, coastal areas (like the Coral Triangle) support the most complex and specialized trophic communities.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Productivity: The availability of energy is a fundamental environmental factor driving the structure of these communities.</p>

<h5>Main implications</h5>

<p>The existence of global trophic analogs provides a powerful new benchmark for conservation and management, directly supporting the UN 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development. This finding means that:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Predictive Modeling: Since functionally analogous communities are likely to respond similarly to drivers like rising temperatures and changing energy availability, we can use this regionalization to better model and project the ecological impacts of global environmental change on ocean biodiversity.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Management: Conservation efforts can be made more effective by focusing on managing functional roles and trophic processes within these newly defined community types, rather than relying solely on traditional species-list based regions.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="machine learning" /><category term="macroecology" /><category term="biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Marine life across the globe organizes into 6 functionally similar trophic communities, driven by temperature and depth.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Climate change may produce severe seagrass biomass losses</title><link href="/impacts-future-climate-change-seagrass-biomass/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate change may produce severe seagrass biomass losses" /><published>2025-01-20T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-20T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/impacts-future-climate-change-seagrass-biomass/"><![CDATA[<p>Seagrass meadows are the unsung heroes of our marine ecosystems, acting as critical carbon sinks (blue carbon) and providing essential habitat that supports immense biodiversity. They are among the most valuable ecosystems on Earth, yet like many coastal habitats, they are currently under threat from intensifying human pressures and a changing climate. Our new research dives deep into how these vital ecosystems will fare in the face of future global warming.</p>

<h5>Knowledge gap</h5>

<p>While we know that seagrasses are declining, previous research has lacked a comprehensive, global-scale estimate of the potential changes in their aboveground biomass (AGB)—the part of the plant that creates critical habitat and stores carbon in the short term—under different climate change scenarios. We needed to move beyond regional studies and distribution modeling to quantify this essential ecological asset worldwide.</p>

<h5>Main approach</h5>

<p>To address this, we employed a sophisticated machine learning approach using a Boosted Regression Trees (BRT) algorithm. This method allowed us to model and quantify the present-day potential AGB of seagrasses across the globe. We then projected future AGB changes under contrasting Shared Socioeconomic Pathway (SSP) scenarios, ranging from the low-emissions scenario (SSP1-1.9, aligned with the Paris Agreement) to high-emissions scenarios (SSP3-7.0 and SSP5-8.5).</p>

<h5>Technological challenge - how we tackle the study</h5>

<p>A major challenge in global ecological modeling is accounting for the immense variability between different species and ensuring the model’s predictions are biologically sound. We tackled this by building robustness into our BRT model:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> We included genus as a fixed effect to account for the major, inherent differences in AGB between seagrass types (e.g., Posidonia has a much higher AGB than Halophila).<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> We incorporated monotonicity constraints, which force the model to follow biologically expected trends (e.g., maximum temperature should generally have a negative effect on AGB). This step was crucial for managing highly correlated predictors like minimum and maximum temperature, ensuring the model’s high accuracy (83% of variability explained) reflected real-world ecological processes.</p>

<h5>Main finding</h5>

<p>Our model estimated a present-day total global seagrass AGB of 0.0673 Pg DW (Petagrams Dry Weight), driven primarily by the seagrass genus and temperature conditions. Under future climate scenarios, we project substantial global losses, with the severity highly dependent on the emission pathway:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> The lower-emission SSP1-1.9 scenario projected a global loss of 9.96% in overall AGB.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> The higher-emission SSP3-7.0 scenario projected a global loss of 10.26% in overall AGB.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Regionally, losses are projected to be most severe in hotspots like the Tropical Eastern Pacific, Eastern Indo-Pacific, and Tropical Atlantic.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Conversely, pronounced increases in AGB (up to 211.22% in the SSP3-7.0 scenario) are projected in the Arctic and Temperate Southern Africa due to poleward range shifts.</p>

<h5>main implications for conservation and management of biodiversity</h5>

<p>This study provides clear evidence that global climate mitigation efforts directly benefit marine conservation. Fulfilling the goals of the Paris Agreement would substantially limit the projected decline in global seagrass biomass, protecting their associated ecosystem services, including carbon sequestration and fisheries support. For conservation managers, the findings offer a vital guide:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Prioritize Protection: Conservation resources must be urgently directed toward high-biomass, high-vulnerability regions, including the Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZs) of countries like Brazil, Costa Rica, Panama, Japan, and China, which are predicted to suffer the largest biomass losses.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Integrate Policy: We advocate for integrating seagrass conservation into National Blue Carbon Policy Assessments to bolster national contributions to the UN 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development goals, ensuring we maintain these critical marine forests for the future.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="machine learning" /><category term="climate change" /><category term="biodiversity" /><category term="seagrass" /><category term="paris agreement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Future climate change could cause up to 10.26% loss in seagrass biomass, stressing the critical need to fulfill the Paris Agreement goals.]]></summary></entry></feed>