<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-05T12:27:53+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BiodiversityDataScience</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ocean transport connecting Greenland’s macroalgae to deep ocean carbon sinks</title><link href="/ocean-transport-vertical-mixing-macroalgae-deep-ocean-carbon-sinks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ocean transport connecting Greenland’s macroalgae to deep ocean carbon sinks" /><published>2026-01-05T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-05T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/ocean-transport-vertical-mixing-macroalgae-deep-ocean-carbon-sinks/"><![CDATA[<p>Beyond the rugged cliffs of Southwest Greenland, a hidden “blue carbon” pump is at work, transporting coastal seaweed into the deep abyss to help regulate our planet’s climate.</p>

<h5>Knowledge gap</h5>
<p>While macroalgae are known for high productivity and carbon assimilation, the specific oceanographic pathways that transport this carbon from rocky shorelines to permanent deep-sea storage have remained largely speculative. Most global carbon export estimates rely on simplifying assumptions because resolving the interplay between biological properties and complex physical ocean transport processes is exceptionally difficult.</p>

<h5>Main approach</h5>
<p>Our study utilized an interdisciplinary testbed in the Southwest Greenland continental shelf and the Labrador Sea to resolve these pathways.  The approach integrated: <i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> High-resolution Sentinel-2 satellite imagery to map the distribution of floating algae mats. <i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Tracking data from 305 surface drifters to quantify transport pathways and residence times. <i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Lagrangian particle tracking models (LPTM) to trace the origins and future sinks of detected algal patches. <i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Large Eddy Simulations (LES) to explore the physical mechanisms behind vertical export.</p>

<h5>Technological challenge - how we tackle the study</h5>
<p>The primary challenge lies in the remote and hostile nature of the Arctic environment. Traditional ship-based observations of deep-sea carbon transport are nearly impossible during intense winter storms when deep convection occurs. To overcome this, we leveraged machine learning-adjacent techniques and numerical simulations to detect nearly 8,000 mats of macroalgae from space and model their behavior in turbulent waters that exceed 2,000 meters in depth.</p>

<h5>Main finding</h5>
<p>Analysis of over 1,300 satellite images revealed more than 7,900 patches of floating macroalgae, confirming their presence far offshore. Surface currents connect the Greenland shelf to the deep Labrador Sea on timescales of roughly 12 to 63 days, which is short enough for the algae to remain intact and buoyant during transit. Crucially, the simulations demonstrated that wintertime deep convection creates vertical velocities strong enough to draw buoyant algae down to depths where their gas-filled vesicles implode under pressure. This “alternating-turbulence pump” causes the algae to lose buoyancy irreversibly and sink to the deep seafloor for long-term sequestration.</p>

<h5>Main implications</h5>
<p>These findings underscore the vital role of macroalgal forests in the global biological carbon pump and their potential as significant “blue carbon” contributors. As climate change warms the Arctic, habitat suitability models predict an expansion of these marine forests. Understanding these transport mechanisms is essential for biodiversity management, as it allows us to better account for the carbon storage provided by coastal ecosystems and protects them from human activities like bottom trawling that may disturb these deep-sea sinks.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="connectivity" /><category term="kelp forests" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Greenland's floating seaweed mats travel via surface currents to deep ocean sinks, where winter mixing forces them to sink and sequester carbon for centuries.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No significant marine aquaculture changes under the sustainable climate scenario</title><link href="/climate-change-effects-marine-aquaculture-sustainable-scenario/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No significant marine aquaculture changes under the sustainable climate scenario" /><published>2025-12-12T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-12T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/climate-change-effects-marine-aquaculture-sustainable-scenario/"><![CDATA[<div style="margin-bottom: 30px">
    <iframe title="" allowtransparency="true" class="border-radius-10" height="150" width="100%" style="border: 2px solid #7e4abeff;min-width: min(100%, 430px);height:150px;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&amp;i=q7pki-1a0cab4-pb&amp;share=0&amp;download=0&amp;fonts=Arial&amp;skin=f6f6f6&amp;font-color=000000&amp;rtl=0&amp;logo_link=episode_page&amp;btn-skin=F6B1BB&amp;size=150" loading="lazy"></iframe>
</div>

<p>As global populations grow, our reliance on the ocean for food has never been higher, yet the stability of marine aquaculture faces an uncertain future under a warming climate.</p>

<h5>Knowledge gap</h5>
<p>While climate impacts have been projected for some finfish and bivalves, approximately 62% of global marine aquaculture production—worth over 55 billion US dollars—remains unassessed for climate sensitivity. Crucial groups such as algae, which constitute the majority of biomass, and crustaceans, the most valuable per weight, have been largely overlooked in long-term global projections.</p>

<h5>Main approach</h5>
<p>Our research group evaluated the climate exposure of 327 marine species—including algae, crustaceans, finfish, molluscs, tunicates, and echinoderms—across their native geographic ranges. We utilized a climate dissimilarity index to quantify the difference between current environmental conditions and those projected by the end of the century. The study analyzed these shifts across three distinct Shared Socioeconomic Pathway (SSP) scenarios, ranging from a “sustainability” future to “fossil fuel development.”</p>

<h5>Technological challenge</h5>
<p>To address the lack of data for many species and the complexity of shifting ocean variables, we employed advanced data science pipelines:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> We used the Bio-ORACLE computational pipeline to generate high-resolution global climate layers for variables including sea temperature, dissolved oxygen, and salinity.</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Our approach utilized the Mahalanobis distance to calculate “sigma dissimilarity,” a metric that normalizes climate novelty based on local intra-annual variability, ensuring meaningful comparisons across different dimensions.</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> We integrated modeled range maps from Aquamaps with manually generated distributions for 80 species derived from literature and databases like FishBase and AlgaeBase.</p>

<h5>Main finding</h5>
<p>The results demonstrate a stark contrast between climate futures. Under the sustainable SSP1-1.9 scenario (1.5°C warming), 41% of Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ) remain entirely unexposed to climate novelty, and high-value groups like crustaceans and echinoderms remain safe. However, as the 1.5°C threshold was surpassed in 2024, more severe scenarios must be considered. Under high-emission pathways (SSP3-7.0 and SSP5-8.5), all current aquaculture regions are projected to experience climate dissimilarity, with semi-enclosed regions like the Baltic, Black, and Red Seas facing the most extreme environmental shifts.</p>

<h5>Main implications</h5>
<p>These findings underscore that widespread mitigation is necessary to ensure the resilience of global food security.  For conservation and industry management:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Cultivating species within their native ranges should be prioritized to reduce the risks associated with non-native species escapes and pathogen introductions.</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Major producers like China, India, and Norway may need to implement within-country relocation or transition to more resilient strains to adapt to changing local climates.</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Some regions, such as Argentina, Pakistan, and Tuvalu, represent significant opportunities for future aquaculture expansion as they are projected to remain climate-resilient even under higher emission scenarios.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="climate change" /><category term="paris agreement" /><category term="biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Marine aquaculture can resist climate change if we meet the 1.5°C Paris Agreement target, but higher emission scenarios threaten 100% of current high-value producing zones.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Monitoring corals using multimodal artificial intelligence</title><link href="/monitor-coral-reefs-multimodal-artificial-intelligence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Monitoring corals using multimodal artificial intelligence" /><published>2025-06-25T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-25T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/monitor-coral-reefs-multimodal-artificial-intelligence/"><![CDATA[<p>This groundbreaking research explores the immense potential of combining Multimodal Artificial Intelligence (AI) with Citizen Science data to overcome critical challenges in marine biodiversity monitoring, particularly in the realm of coral reefs.</p>

<h5>Knowledge gap</h5>
<p>Global marine conservation efforts are severely hampered by a pervasive lack of current, consistent data and chronic underfunding. Monitoring biodiversity in remote, complex ecosystems like coral reefs is traditionally expensive, requiring specialized equipment and expert taxonomic knowledge. This results in:
<br /><br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Massive Data Deficiencies: Less than 6% of described species have been assessed for extinction risk by the IUCN, and up to 17,000 of those are “data deficient.” This gap is most pronounced in marine ecosystems.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Slow Data Processing: Citizen Science programs, like the invaluable Reef Life Survey (RLS), are generating high-quality image data much faster than expert taxonomists can label them. This creates a bottleneck that limits the real-world impact of citizen efforts.</p>

<h5>Main approach</h5>
<p>We hypothesized that Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs)—the cutting-edge AI architecture that can process both image and text data—could effectively leverage vast Citizen Science datasets to automate the laborious task of benthic image classification. Our approach specifically focused on:
<br /><br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Leveraging Citizen Science Data: Using tens of thousands of seabed images and their multi-label annotations from the Reef Life Survey (RLS) project.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Multimodal AI: Utilizing the Qwen-2.5-VL MLLM family, which are capable of interpreting images of the seafloor and the associated labels simultaneously.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Advanced Fine-Tuning: Applying efficient fine-tuning techniques (QLoRA) to specialize a pre-trained, general-purpose MLLM for the complex, domain-specific task of classifying benthic organisms and substrate.</p>

<h5>Technological challenge - how we tackle the study</h5>
<p>The research was a rigorous exploration of optimizing MLLMs for this specific task. We addressed two main technological challenges:
<br /><br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Optimizing Untrained Model Performance (Prompt Engineering): before fine-tuning, we tested various prompt engineering techniques—the art of giving the AI better instructions—to get the best possible results from the general-purpose model.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Achieving Domain Expertise (Fine-Tuning): we employed QLoRA to efficiently adapt the MLLMs to the RLS dataset. Our experiments compared different model sizes (3B vs. 7B parameters) and the effect of adding contextual data (like geographic co-ordinates) during training.</p>

<h5>Main finding</h5>
<p>The top-performing model—the 7B parameter MLLM fine-tuned on the largest dataset—achieved an average F1-score of 0.45. This score is directly comparable to previous high-performing, task-specific Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) models that have been integrated into professional marine monitoring workflows, such as those used by NOAA. Key Takeaways from the Final Model:
<br /><br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> High-Frequency Labels: The model excelled at identifying common, well-represented classes like Ecklonia radiata (a type of kelp), achieving an F1-score of 0.706.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Imbalanced Data Challenge: The model struggled with rare species (low-frequency classes), which is a common limitation when dealing with real-world, highly imbalanced biodiversity datasets.</p>

<h5>Main implications</h5>
<p>This research validates Multimodal Large Language Models as a robust, scalable, and powerful alternative to traditional Computer Vision models (like CNNs) for ecological classification. The combined approach of Citizen Science and MLLMs offers a clear path to:
<br /><br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Unlock the RLS Data Archive: Significantly accelerate the labeling of the vast, high-quality RLS photo archives, turning raw data into actionable biodiversity insights faster than ever before.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Scale Global Monitoring: Create a foundation for global, cost-effective monitoring programs that can leverage publicly submitted imagery for real-time assessment of coral reef health.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Advance AI in Ecology: Establish MLLMs and transformer architecture as a strong contender in the field of marine and terrestrial ecology, which is currently dominated by CNNs.</p>

<p>With further research into increasing training data, scaling to even larger models (32B/72B), and optimizing for low-frequency species, the potential for MLLMs to exceed current benthic classification models is considerable, fundamentally enhancing our ability to protect the world’s oceans.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="artificial intelligence" /><category term="biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The prospects of using multimodal Artificial Intelligence with Citizen Science to monitor Coral reefs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cold‐Water coral redistribution under climate change</title><link href="/coral-redistribution-under-climate-change-biodiversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cold‐Water coral redistribution under climate change" /><published>2025-06-25T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-25T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/coral-redistribution-under-climate-change-biodiversity/"><![CDATA[<div style="margin-bottom: 30px">
    <iframe title="" allowtransparency="true" class="border-radius-10" height="150" width="100%" style="border: 2px solid #7e4abeff;min-width: min(100%, 430px);height:150px;" scrolling="no" data-name="pb-iframe-player" src="https://www.podbean.com/player-v2/?from=embed&amp;i=j2bm5-19a2734-pb&amp;share=0&amp;download=0&amp;fonts=Arial&amp;skin=f6f6f6&amp;font-color=000000&amp;rtl=0&amp;logo_link=episode_page&amp;btn-skin=F6B1BB&amp;size=150" loading="lazy"></iframe>
</div>

<p>Cold-water corals (CWCs) are critical ecosystem-structuring species that provide essential services, from continental shelves to abyssal depths. They create complex, three-dimensional habitats, acting as feeding, breeding, and nursery grounds for a wide range of commercially important fish and invertebrates. Their future, however, is heavily dependent on the planet’s climate trajectory.</p>

<h5>The critical knowledge gap</h5>

<p>Despite their immense ecological importance, knowledge of the global distribution, diversity patterns, and overall vulnerability of cold-water corals to climate change remains severely limited. This knowledge gap constrains effective, large-scale conservation strategies, particularly the design of robust Marine Protected Areas (MPAs) needed to meet global protection targets.</p>

<h5>Our main approach</h5>

<p>We conducted the most extensive global assessment of CWC biogeography to date, analyzing 741 species spanning six major taxonomic groups. We used this data to predict species distributions under present-day conditions and project future shifts under two contrasting end-of-century climate scenarios: the low-emission SSP1-1.9 (aligned with the Paris Agreement) and the high-emission SSP3-7.0. Our analysis was based on three pillars:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Mapping global species richness and identifying biodiversity hotspots.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Delineating ten distinct cold-water coral bioregions based on species co-occurrence.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Quantifying projected shifts in species richness, community turnover, and identifying climate refugia.</p>

<h5>Technological challenge: how we tackle the study</h5>

<p>To accurately model the distribution of these complex, low-dispersal organisms, we employed an ensemble of high-performance machine learning Species Distribution Models (SDMs), including Boosted Regression Trees (BRT), Adaptive Boosting (AdaBoost), and Extreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost). Our key methodological innovations included:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Monotonicity constraints: We applied ecological constraints to the models (e.g., assuming higher maximum temperature has a negative effect), ensuring the predictions were biologically realistic and reducing the risk of overfitting.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Dispersal constraints: To account for the slow growth rates and limited dispersal of CWCs, we clipped distribution maps using a maximum dispersal constraint of 200km, which significantly reduced overprediction.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Bioregion validation: We used k-means clustering to delineate the ten bioregions and statistically confirmed their distinctiveness using Analysis of Similarities (ANOSIM).</p>

<h5>The main finding</h5>

<p>Our results showed major biodiversity hotspots in the Gulf of Mexico and the Caribbean Sea, and delineated ten distinct bioregions, each with varying species richness, depth distribution patterns, and generally low levels of endemicity.</p>

<div class="border-radius-10 margin-top-20" style="background-color: white; padding: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px">
<img src="/assets/images/posts/gcb70563-fig-0002-m.webp" />
</div>
<p>Fig. Present-day species richness distribution for 741 species of cold-water corals.</p>

<p>While the global extent of suitable CWC habitat is projected to persist, species-level redistributions will drive dramatic change, with the magnitude strongly tied to emission levels. We identified the Gulf of Mexico and the Caribbean Sea as major present-day biodiversity hotspots. Under the high-emission scenario (SSP3-7.0), we projected:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Widespread poleward and depth shifts, with average species distribution projected to deepen by 26.0m.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Significant biodiversity loss in shallow and low-latitude regions, with the Central Western Atlantic projected to lose up to 66 species.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Richness gains primarily concentrated in deeper offshore areas and the Arctic, indicating potential but fragile new habitats.</p>

<div class="border-radius-10 margin-top-20" style="background-color: white; padding: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px">
<img src="/assets/images/posts/gcb70563-fig-0004-m.webp" />
</div>
<p>Fig. Projected end-of-century changes under SSP1-1.9 and SSP3-7.0 in (a, b) species richness, (c, d) climate refugia, and (e, f) community turnover of cold-water corals. Climate refugia represent the fraction of species predicted to retain suitable habitat (0 = none persist; 1 = all persist). Turnover ranges from 0 (no change in species composition) to 1 (complete replacement). Areas with no species present are shown in white.</p>

<h5>Main implications for conservation and management of biodiversity</h5>

<p>Our findings underscore the urgent need for global climate action aligned with the Paris Agreement. The study provides an actionable framework to support the UN 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development and the post-2020 Global Biodiversity Framework.</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Prioritizing Conservation: We pinpoint biodiversity hotspots and emerging climate refugia, offering crucial guidance for the strategic designation of new MPAs.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Addressing Synergistic Risks: Our data highlights the amplification of risks in regions like the Gulf of Mexico, where a global CWC hotspot overlaps with major oil and gas extraction zones, requiring immediate, targeted mitigation.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Spatially Explicit Strategies: The ten newly defined bioregions, structured primarily by depth and species composition, enable conservation efforts to be tailored precisely to the unique assemblage of species found in each region.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="climate change" /><category term="conservation" /><category term="biodiversity" /><category term="paris agreement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Climate change will force cold-water corals to shift poleward and deeper, causing significant biodiversity loss in shallow, low-latitude regions unless global emissions are drastically reduced.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Global estimates of ocean current connectivity</title><link href="/global-estimates-ocean-current-connectivity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Global estimates of ocean current connectivity" /><published>2025-06-25T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-06-25T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/global-estimates-ocean-current-connectivity/"><![CDATA[<p>How do marine species travel the world? Ocean currents act as “highways” for marine life, moving larvae, individuals, and genetic material between populations.</p>

<p>But understanding these connections on a global scale, and how they shape biodiversity, has been almost impossible. We generated the first-ever global estimates of ocean current connectivity, tracking 204 million particles over 21 years. This new dataset is a benchmark for marine conservation and climate change resilience.</p>

<h5>Knowledge gap</h5>
<p>Despite its importance, a comprehensive, high-resolution global dataset of oceanographic connectivity has been missing. Traditional studies often rely on overly simple models that fail to capture the complex, variable, and asymmetric dispersal patterns created by real-world ocean currents. This knowledge gap has hindered our ability to understand species’ dispersal and develop effective large-scale conservation strategies, especially for building resilience to climate change.</p>

<h5>Main approach</h5>
<p>We tackled this gap by creating the first comprehensive dataset of connectivity estimates (both probability and travel time) along all the world’s coastlines. We used a robust biophysical model that simulates passive dispersal, essentially tracking “virtual larvae” carried by ocean currents.</p>

<h5>Technological challenge - how we tackle the study</h5>
<p>The scale of this challenge was immense. Our model used 21 years of daily, high-resolution global ocean current data (GLORYS12V1). We released particles daily from 26,642 coastal sites worldwide, running Lagrangian simulations to track over 204 million individual particle trajectories. To make this massive dataset (which includes 195 million recorded connectivity events) accessible and useful, we also developed <b>coastalNet</b>, an R package designed to streamline the access, analysis, and visualization of the connectivity data.</p>

<h5>Main finding</h5>
<p>The result is a new, publicly available benchmark dataset for oceanographic connectivity research. It provides pairwise probabilities and travel times between coastal locations, which can be flexibly combined with species-specific biological traits. Researchers can now filter the data by planktonic duration (from hours up to 180 days) and by seasonality (spawning periods) to create realistic dispersal models for thousands of different marine species.</p>

<h5>Main implications</h5>
<p>This dataset is a powerful new tool for marine conservation and management. It provides the critical data needed to:
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Inform more effective conservation strategies, such as designing and assessing networks of Marine Protected Areas.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Understand and predict species’ resilience and potential for range expansion under climate change.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Enable a deeper exploration of the complex dynamics that shape coastal marine ecosystems.
<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Calculate multi-generational “stepping-stone” connectivity, identifying crucial pathways for dispersal over long distances.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="data" /><category term="archived" /><category term="connectivity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Global estimates of ocean current connectivity, a benchmark for marine conservation and climate change resilience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mapping global shipless areas and conflicts with biodiversity</title><link href="/global-shipless-areas-conflict-with-biodiversity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping global shipless areas and conflicts with biodiversity" /><published>2025-04-25T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-04-25T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/global-shipless-areas-conflict-with-biodiversity/"><![CDATA[<h5>The knowledge gap</h5>
<p>Despite clear evidence that shipping activity—through vessel collisions, noise pollution, and disturbance—severely impacts marine megafauna like cetaceans, sea turtles, pinnipeds, and seabirds, there was no comprehensive global map to guide conservation efforts. We lacked the vital knowledge to distinguish between undisturbed biodiversity refuges and high-risk conflict zones at a planetary scale.</p>

<h5>Main approach</h5>
<p>We conducted a global assessment by overlaying two critical layers: a composite measure of species richness for the four vulnerable faunal groups and vessel density derived from Automatic Identification System (AIS) data. By classifying both metrics into terciles (low, medium, high), we were able to define two new conservation categories:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Priority Preservation Areas (PPAs): Regions of high species richness overlapping with low or minimal shipping activity (biodiversity refuges).<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Priority Mitigation Areas (PMAs): Regions of high species richness overlapping with high shipping density (high-risk conflict zones)</p>

<h5>Technological challenge - how we tackle the study</h5>
<p>The core challenge was translating vast, continuous streams of global maritime traffic (AIS data) and highly dynamic species distribution models (AquaMaps and BirdLife) into a single, actionable risk assessment framework. We used a bivariate mapping approach in R to synthesize these complex datasets, enabling us to quantify the interplay between biodiversity value and potential impact risk across every marine grid cell, making the findings globally consistent and scalable.</p>

<h5>Main finding</h5>
<p>Our maps reveal that biodiversity is concentrated in two major zones. PPAs—our ocean’s last large, undisturbed refuges—are predominantly found in the remote, high southern latitudes, near Antarctica. Conversely, PMAs are clustered along coastlines and in critical trans-oceanic passages, especially in the mid-Pacific, southern Indian Ocean, and South Atlantic.</p>

<div class="border-radius-10 margin-top-20" style="background-color: white; padding: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px">
<img src="/assets/images/posts/1-s2.0-S0006320725004689-gr1_lrg.jpg" />
</div>
<p>Fig. Distribution of shipless areas (blue), representing regions with minimal or negligible vessel activity. Marine Protected Areas (&gt;100,000 ha) are overlaid in green, while Exclusive Economic Zone boundaries are marked with dotted lines.</p>

<p>Crucially, we found that existing Marine Protected Areas (MPAs) are currently falling short: they cover only 15.2% of PPAs and 16.2% of PMAs, leaving vast priority areas unprotected or unmanaged.</p>

<h5>Main implications for conservation and management of biodiversity</h5>
<p>These findings provide a clear roadmap for achieving global marine conservation goals, including the UN 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development and the 30 x 30 target. We need a dual-strategy approach to marine spatial planning:</p>

<p><i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Preserve: Immediately designate the identified PPAs as new MPAs or equivalent conservation measures to safeguard these essential, shipless biodiversity refuges before future traffic routes encroach.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Mitigate: Implement targeted shipping management strategies in PMAs, such as mandatory vessel speed reductions to minimize lethal collisions and noise pollution, and dynamic traffic rerouting to avoid seasonal biodiversity hotspots.<br />
<i class="fas fa-angle-double-right"></i> Govern: Use this framework to inform international policies on the High Seas, helping countries and organizations balance vital maritime trade with the urgent need to protect vulnerable marine ecosystems.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="featured" /><category term="conservation" /><category term="biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The global maritime industry, the lifeblood of our modern economy, is rapidly expanding, but its growing footprint poses an immense, quantified threat to the ocean's largest inhabitants.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html"></title><link href="/marine-forever-211/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2025-04-01T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-04-01T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-forever-211/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="archived" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html"></title><link href="/marine-forever-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2025-03-10T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-10T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-forever-3/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="archived" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html"></title><link href="/marine-forever-5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2025-03-10T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-10T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-forever-5/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="archived" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html"></title><link href="/marine-forever-211/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2025-03-01T02:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-01T02:30:00+00:00</updated><id>/P</id><content type="html" xml:base="/marine-forever-211/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="archived" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>