<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-11T16:55:10+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Climate change and the future diversity of seagrasses</title><link href="/climate-change-future-diversity-seagrasses-global/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate change and the future diversity of seagrasses" /><published>2024-10-12T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-12T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/climate-change-future-diversity-seagrasses-global/"><![CDATA[<p>In our latest study, we explored the potentially  effects of climate change on seagrass ecosystems, which play a crucial role in marine habitats. These habitat-forming species face growing threats, yet there remains a critical gap in global predictive frameworks that could help forecast their future distribution and richness. Our research aimed to fill this gap by estimating future changes in seagrass species richness, community composition, and identifying potential areas of climatic refugia under different climate scenarios.</p>

<p><b>Key findings</b></p>

<p>Global Scope: Using a globally integrated approach, we assessed seagrass species distributions from 2010-2020, and modeled their future under three Shared Socioeconomic Pathways (SSPs) for the period from 2090-2100.</p>

<p>Current Extent: The current global extent of seagrass habitats is estimated at 917,169 km², with high species richness particularly concentrated in regions like Temperate Australasia, the Indo-Pacific, and the Temperate North Pacific.</p>

<p>Future Projections: Our projections indicate that climate change will drive a significant spatial redistribution of seagrass species, including expansions into the Arctic, losses in lower latitudes, and shifts into deeper waters. Interestingly, despite these redistributions, the total global extent occupied by seagrasses is predicted to remain relatively stable, with only a 5% change overall.</p>

<p>Species Richness &amp; Climate Refugia: As climate scenarios become more extreme (SSP3-7.0 and SSP5-8.5), species richness is predicted to increase in polar regions while declining in tropical zones. Climatic refugia, critical for the survival of many species, are expected to persist but diminish under high-emission scenarios. Even in areas where seagrass species persist, we anticipate widespread changes in community composition.</p>

<p><b>Why this matters?</b></p>

<p>This study offers a valuable baseline for understanding and anticipating the impact of climate change on seagrass ecosystems. Seagrasses provide essential services such as carbon sequestration, coastal protection, and habitats for marine biodiversity. As these ecosystems shift, proactive measures will be necessary to mitigate the cascading consequences for marine life and the human communities that depend on them.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In our latest study, we explored the potentially effects of climate change on seagrass ecosystems, which play a crucial role in marine habitats. These habitat-forming species face growing threats, yet there remains a critical gap in global predictive frameworks that could help forecast their future distribution and richness. Our research aimed to fill this gap by estimating future changes in seagrass species richness, community composition, and identifying potential areas of climatic refugia under different climate scenarios.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Climate change challenges Marine Protected Areas in Europe</title><link href="/commercial-fish-species-threatened-climate-change/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate change challenges Marine Protected Areas in Europe" /><published>2024-06-12T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-12T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/commercial-fish-species-threatened-climate-change/"><![CDATA[<p>Our latest research addresses a critical concern for marine conservation: the impact of projected climate change on Marine Protected Areas (MPAs) in Europe. As climate change progresses, the effectiveness of MPAs in preserving marine species and habitats may be significantly challenged. Our study evaluates how 398 threatened and commercially important species within European MPAs could be affected by novel climatic conditions through the end of the 21st century.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p><b>Key findings: It’s all about the Paris Agreement</b></p>

<p>Using multivariate analyses, we assessed the future exposure to changes in temperature, oxygen, pH, and primary productivity under two different climate scenarios: a low emission scenario (SSP1–1.9) and a high emission scenario (SSP5–8.5). Our findings are concerning:</p>

<p>Under the low emission scenario (SSP1–1.9):</p>

<p>Approximately 6.5% of species and 0.5% of European MPAs may face risk from novel climatic conditions.
Under the high emission scenario (SSP5–8.5):</p>

<p>A staggering 87% of MPAs and 80% of species are projected to be at risk. Particularly vulnerable regions include enclosed and semi-enclosed seas like the Baltic Sea and the Black Sea, where nearly all species could be exposed to novel or extremely novel conditions.</p>

<p>In contrast, areas such as the Norwegian Sea, North-East Atlantic, and western parts of the Mediterranean and North Seas are expected to be less impacted.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p><b>Why this matters?</b></p>

<p>This research underscores the urgent need for enhanced conservation efforts and innovative governance strategies to protect marine biodiversity. Our results suggest that current marine governance in Europe may not be sufficient to ensure the resilience and effectiveness of MPAs in the face of climate change. Consequently, it is imperative to meet the targets set by the Paris Agreement and develop forward-thinking approaches to marine conservation.</p>

<p>We hope this study will inform and inspire policymakers, conservationists, and the public about the importance of proactive measures to safeguard our marine ecosystems for future generations.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Our latest research addresses a critical concern for marine conservation: the impact of projected climate change on Marine Protected Areas (MPAs) in Europe. As climate change progresses, the effectiveness of MPAs in preserving marine species and habitats may be significantly challenged. Our study evaluates how 398 threatened and commercially important species within European MPAs could be affected by novel climatic conditions through the end of the 21st century.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Past and future climate effects on population structure and diversity of North Pacific surfgrasses</title><link href="/past-future-climate-effects-surfgrasses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Past and future climate effects on population structure and diversity of North Pacific surfgrasses" /><published>2024-06-01T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-06-01T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/past-future-climate-effects-surfgrasses/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">The key role of seaweed forests in global carbon sequestration</title><link href="/seaweed-forests-global-carbon-sequestration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The key role of seaweed forests in global carbon sequestration" /><published>2024-05-20T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-20T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/seaweed-forests-global-carbon-sequestration/"><![CDATA[<p>The coastal ocean plays a crucial role as a global carbon sink, essential for climate change mitigation efforts and the achievement of the Paris Agreement targets. This critical function also supports biodiversity and other ecosystem services. However, a significant gap in our understanding of marine carbon budgets is the fate of carbon exported from seaweed forests, the largest vegetated ecosystems along our coasts.</p>

<p>Our research has provided groundbreaking national and global estimates of particulate carbon export from seaweed forests to depths below 200 meters, revealing that this process accounts for 3-4% of the ocean’s carbon sink capacity. The study utilized sophisticated models to assess seaweed forest extent, production, decomposition, and the exchange of water between the continental shelf and the open ocean.</p>

<p><b>Key findings:</b></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Seaweed Carbon Export: On average, 15% of seaweed production is exported beyond the continental shelf. This translates to an estimated 56 teragrams of carbon per year (TgC yr−1), with a range between 10 and 170 TgC yr−1.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Sequestration Potential: Of the exported carbon, it is estimated that 4 to 44 Tg of seaweed-derived carbon could be sequestered for up to 100 years at depths below 200 meters annually.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>These insights underscore the significant but previously underappreciated role of seaweed forests in carbon sequestration. Although the study did not account for shelf burial and dissolved and refractory carbon pathways, it highlights the substantial potential of seaweed as a natural carbon sink.</p>

<p><b>Implications for conservation and climate mitigation</b></p>

<p>Understanding the full extent of seaweed carbon sequestration is crucial for guiding conservation efforts, particularly as seaweed forests face global declines. Protecting and restoring these ecosystems could enhance their carbon sequestration potential, contributing to climate mitigation strategies.</p>

<p>This research underscores the importance of seaweed forests in the global carbon cycle. By continuing to investigate and understand the mechanisms behind seaweed carbon export and sequestration, we can better inform conservation policies and climate change mitigation efforts. Protecting these vital ecosystems is not only essential for biodiversity but also for sustaining their role as natural carbon sinks in our fight against climate change.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The coastal ocean plays a crucial role as a global carbon sink, essential for climate change mitigation efforts and the achievement of the Paris Agreement targets. This critical function also supports biodiversity and other ecosystem services. However, a significant gap in our understanding of marine carbon budgets is the fate of carbon exported from seaweed forests, the largest vegetated ecosystems along our coasts.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Ocean currents shaping genetic differentiation of marine forests</title><link href="/role-ocean-currents-marine-forests-differentiation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ocean currents shaping genetic differentiation of marine forests" /><published>2024-05-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/role-ocean-currents-marine-forests-differentiation/"><![CDATA[<p>The genetic diversity of marine forests arises from complex eco-evolutionary interactions. Our research focuses on the significant role that oceanographic connectivity—driven by water transport and dispersal—plays in shaping this diversity on a global scale.</p>

<p><b>Key findings: It’s all about connections</b></p>

<p>It turns out that ocean currents play a much bigger role than previously thought in shaping the genetic makeup of marine forests across the globe. These currents act as underwater highways, carrying propagules from one population to another.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Eco-Evolutionary Puzzle: We combined genetic data from nearly 700 seaweed populations with cutting-edge models of ocean currents. This allowed us to piece together the complex puzzle of how site-specific factors, ocean connectivity, and even rare long-distance dispersal events interact to shape genetic diversity.</li>
  <li>The 18.7% Surprise: Our research shows that almost one-fifth (18.7%) of the variation in genetic diversity across marine forests can be directly linked to the patterns of ocean circulation. This is a significant finding!</li>
  <li>Global Implications: This isn’t just about seaweed. Understanding how connected different populations are has major implications for marine conservation. It means we can better identify which areas to protect, ensuring that these vital ecosystems remain healthy and resilient in the face of climate change and other threats.</li>
</ol>

<p><br /></p>

<p><b>Why this matters?</b></p>

<p>Marine forests are like the underwater equivalent of rainforests – teeming with life and providing essential habitats for countless species. They also play a key role in capturing carbon and supporting fisheries. By understanding the drivers that shape their genetic diversity, we’re taking a big step towards safeguarding these precious ecosystems for future generations.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The genetic diversity of marine forests arises from complex eco-evolutionary interactions. Our research focuses on the significant role that oceanographic connectivity—driven by water transport and dispersal—plays in shaping this diversity on a global scale.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">A global dataset of demosponge distribution records</title><link href="/dataset-marine-sponges-distribution-records/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A global dataset of demosponge distribution records" /><published>2024-05-09T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-09T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dataset-marine-sponges-distribution-records/"><![CDATA[<p>Demosponges, a dominant group within the sponge phylum, play crucial roles in the health of our oceans. These organisms create intricate habitats for marine life and are integral to nutrient cycling in underwater ecosystems. Understanding their biodiversity and distribution is vital for ocean conservation, yet accurate datasets can be hard to come by.  Errors in species identification, location data, and inconsistent formatting across different sources often hinder reliable research.</p>

<p>Our team has addressed these challenges by developing a comprehensive, quality-controlled dataset focused specifically on Demospongiae occurrence records. We have aggregated data from multiple sources, carefully checked for errors, and cross-referenced records with expert knowledge on the expected geographic and depth ranges of each species. The dataset is formatted in the Darwin Core Standard, making it easy to use with a wide range of research tools.</p>

<p>This dataset offers marine scientists a powerful resource for investigating demosponge diversity patterns, including hotspots of species richness and unique species (endemism). It can also help predict how sponge populations might shift in response to climate change, guiding more effective conservation measures. We are committed to the principle of making research data openly accessible. By providing this dataset, we hope to advance marine science and our understanding of Earth’s precious oceans.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Data" /><category term="Biodiversity" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Demosponges, a dominant group within the sponge phylum, play crucial roles in the health of our oceans. These organisms create intricate habitats for marine life and are integral to nutrient cycling in underwater ecosystems. Understanding their biodiversity and distribution is vital for ocean conservation, yet accurate datasets can be hard to come by. Errors in species identification, location data, and inconsistent formatting across different sources often hinder reliable research.]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Cryptic diversity in southern African kelp</title><link href="/cryptic-diversity-southern-africa/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cryptic diversity in southern African kelp" /><published>2024-04-19T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-19T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/cryptic-diversity-southern-africa/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Multidisciplinary estimates of connectivity and population structure suggest the use of multiple units for the conservation and management of meagre, Argyrosomus regius</title><link href="/multidisciplinary-estimates-connectivity-meagre/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multidisciplinary estimates of connectivity and population structure suggest the use of multiple units for the conservation and management of meagre, Argyrosomus regius" /><published>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/multidisciplinary-estimates-connectivity-meagre/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Trans-Arctic asymmetries, melting pots and weak species cohesion in the low-dispersal amphiboreal seaweed Fucus distichus</title><link href="/asymmetries-seaweed-fucus-distichus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trans-Arctic asymmetries, melting pots and weak species cohesion in the low-dispersal amphiboreal seaweed Fucus distichus" /><published>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/asymmetries-seaweed-fucus-distichus/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Incorporating physiological knowledge into correlative species distribution models minimizes bias introduced by the choice of calibration area</title><link href="/physiological-knowledge-distribution-models/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Incorporating physiological knowledge into correlative species distribution models minimizes bias introduced by the choice of calibration area" /><published>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T03:30:00+01:00</updated><id>/J</id><content type="html" xml:base="/physiological-knowledge-distribution-models/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="" /><category term="" /><category term="" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>